Finding Aid for Edson Read Sunderland Papers 1892-1959
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Speeches and Articles
  E. Blythe Stason, Dean of the Law School of the University of Michigan at the time of Sunderland's death, pointed out in a Michigan Law Review tribute that, "Beginning in 1915, [Sunderland] wrote constantly, year after year, for the next thirty-five years...By following the paths...one is able to trace the development of most, if not all, of the new features of our present civil procedure." A complete bibliography of this work, Edson Read Sunderland: A record of some of the results of a lifetime devoted to legal research and the teaching of law" is held at the Bentley (Bentley Historical Library call number DB/2/S958/B582). The Speeches and Articles series is a rich resource, particularly as an adjunct to the bibliographical compilation and also to Sunderland's published articles, many of which are not included in the collection, but likely available elsewhere. Articles, drafts and reprints included in the series often contain annotations that reveal threads as a piece develops, and speeches usually eventually appeared in written form in a journal or newspaper article.
  - 1915-1930
    - "The Inefficiency of the American Jury," 1915 (Box 16)
    - "An Appraisal of English Procedure," 1925 (Box 16)
    - "Hundred Years' War for Legal Reform in England," 1926 (Box 16)
    - "Judicial Reform in England in the Nineteenth Century," 1926 (Box 16)
    - "English and American Administration of Justice," 1927 (Box 16)
    - "Problem of Trying Issues," 1927 (Box 16)
    - "Problems of Appellate Review," 1928 (Box 16)
    - "Problems of Appellate Procedures," 1928 (Box 16)
    - "Simplification of Appellate Procedure," 1928 (Box 16)
    - "The Regulation of Legal Procedure," 1928 (Box 16)
    - "English and American Courts of Justice," 1929 (Box 16)
    - "The Proper Function of the Appellate Court," 1929 (Box 16)
    - "The Proposed Revision of Michigan Rules of Practice," 1929 (Box 16)
    - "Symposium on the Conditions for and the Aims and Methods of Legal Research," (Box 16)
    - "Discussion on Revised Circuit Court Rules," 1930 (Box 16)
    - "New Court Rules and Their Effect on Practice," 1930 (Box 16)
  - 1931-1935
    - "Lawyer's Club Handbook Writings," 1931-1932 (Box 16)
    - "Constitutionality of the Practice," 1932 (Box 16)
    - "Court Rules of Michigan," 1932 Revision (Box 16)
    - "Problems in Jurisdiction," 1932 (Box 16)
    - "Ways and Means of Improving the Administration of Justice," 1932 (Box 16)
    - "Broadcast for the American Bar Association," 1933 (Box 16)
    - "Discovery Before Trial," 1933 (Box 16)
    - "Survey of the Opportunities for Improving the Administration of Civil Justice," 1933 (Box 16)
    - "Function and Organization of a Judicial Council," 1934 (Box 16)
    - "Notes on the Illinois Civil Practice Act," University of Chicago 1934 (Box 16)
    - "Regulation of Procedure," 1934 (Box 16)
    - "Report of the Special Committee on Intermediate Appellate Courts," 1934 (Box 16)
    - "Simplification of the Appellate Procedure," 1934 (Box 16)
    - "Judicial Council as Rule Making Agency," 1934 (Box 17)
    - "Judicial Council as Rule Making Agency," 1935 (Box 17)
    - "Supplemental Study of the Libel Laws of the United States," 1935 (Box 17)
  - 1936-1940
    - "Findings of Fact and Conclusions of Law," 1936 (Box 17)
    - "Trial by Jury," Cincinnati Conference 1937 (Box 17)
    - "Federal Rules as Related to Michigan Practice," 1937-38 (Box 17)
    - "Justice in the Federal Courts," 1938 (Box 17)
    - "Rules of Court Governing Practice and Procedure," 1938 (Box 17)
    - "The Scope of Judicial Review," 1938 (Box 17)
    - "Three Lectures Given Before the Toledo Bar Association on the New Federal Rules of Civil Procedure," 1938 (Box 17)
    - "Toledo Institute on Federal Rules," 1938 (Box 17)
    - "Trends in Procedural Law," 1938 (Box 17)
    - "Discovery Before Trial Under the New Federal Rules," 1939 (Box 17)
    - "Present Methods of Judicial Selection," 1939 (Box 17)
    - "Pre-Trial Stage of Litigation," 1939 (Box 17)
    - "Vassar Lecture," 1939 (Box 17)
  - 1941-1951
    - "Improvement of Appellate Procedure," Iowa Bar Association 1940 (Box 17)
    - "Discovery before Trial," 1940, 3 folders (Box 17)
    - "Judicial Council as an Aid to the Administration of Justice," 1940 (Box 17)
    - "The Administration of Justice in the United States," Seminar for South American Students 1942 (Box 17)
    - "Tennessee University Law School Institute," 1942 (Box 17)
    - "Pre-Trial Procedure," 1944 (Box 17)
    - "The County as a Territorial Unit for a Minor Court System," 1945 (Box 17)
    - "Society for Michigan Mental Hygiene," 1946 (Box 17)
    - "The Need for a Modern Substitute for Justice of the Peace," 1946 (Box 17)
    - "The Law of Copyright as Applied to Photographs and Photographic Reproductions," 1947. (Box 17)
    - "Implementing the Rule Making Power," American Political Science Meeting 1949 (Box 17)
    - "Study of the Courts of the Detroit Metropolitan District," 1950 (Box 17)
    - "County Court Bill," Farm Bureau Broadcast 1951 (Box 17)
  - Undated
    - "Argument in Support of Senate Bill 759" (Box 17)
    - "Commitment of Insane Persons," Michigan Society for Mental Hygiene (Box 17)
    - "Declaratory Judgments in Michigan" (Box 17)
    - "Ethics of Law, Notes on..." (Box 17)
    - "Minimal Standards of Judicial Administration" (Box 17)
    - "Modern English Legal Practice" (Box 17)
    - "Principles Underlying the New Federal Rules of Civil Procedure" (Box 17)
    - "Status and Personnel of Justice of the Peace Courts" (Box 17)
    - "Trial by Jury" (Box 17)
    - Book Reviews (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Articles, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Notes for "addresses", 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Potential law review subjects (Box 17)
  - Printed
    - 1900-1926
      - "The Art of Legal Practice," 1900 (Box 18)
      - "English Law as an Exponent of English History," 1909 (Box 18)
      - "The Sheriff's Return," 1916 (Box 18)
      - "A Modern Evolution in Remedial Rights -- The Declaratory Judgment," 1917 (Box 18)
      - "Verdicts, General and Special," 1920 (Box 18)
      - "The Reform of Civil Procedure," 1923 (Box 18)
      - "An Appraisal of English Procedure," 1925 (Box 18)
      - "The Professional Ideals of the Lawyer," Book Review 1926 (Box 18)
      - "Hundred Years' War for Legal Reform in England," 1926 (Box 18)
      - "Modern English Legal Practice," 1926 (Box 18)
      - "The English Struggle for Procedural Reform," 1926 (Box 18)
      - "The Exercise of the Rule Making Power," 1926 (Box 18)
    - 1927-1933
      - "Explanation of Michigan situation, Appendix 'G'," 1929 (Box 18)
      - "Simplification of Appellate Procedure," 1929 (Box 18)
      - "The Proper Function of an Appellate Court," 1930 (Box 18)
      - "The Law Schools and the Legal Profession," 1931 (Box 18)
      - "The New Michigan Court Rules," 1931 (Box 18)
      - "Discovery before Trial," 1933 (Box 18)
      - "Progress toward a Better Administration of Justice," 1933 (Box 18)
      - "Scope and Method of Discovery before Trial," 1933 (Box 18)
      - "The Problem of Double Appeals," 1933 (Box 18)
      - "The Provisions Relating to Trial Practice in the New Illinois Civil Practice Act," 1933 (Box 18)
    - 1934-1937
      - "Observations on the Illinois Civil Practice Act," 1934 (Box 18)
      - "The Burden of Double Appeals under a System of Intermediate Appellate Courts," 1934 (Box 18)
      - "The Function and Organization of a Judicial Council," 1934 (Box 18)
      - "The Grant of Rule-Making Power to the Supreme Court of the United States," 1934 (Box 18)
      - "Judicial Administration: It's Scope and Methods 1935 (Box 18)
      - "Report of the Commission on Administration of Justice in New York State," 1935 (Box 18)
      - "Findings of Fact and Conclusions of Law in Cases Where Juries are Waived," 1937 (Box 18)
      - "The Theory and Practice of Pre-Trial Procedure," 1937 (Box 18)
    - 1938-1939 (Box 19)
      - "Legal Institute on New Federal Rules," 1938 (Box 19)
      - "New Federal Rules," 1938 (Box 19)
      - "New Federal Rules for Civil Procedure," 1938 (Box 19)
      - "The Availability of the New Federal Rules for Use in the State Courts of Ohio," 1938 (Box 19)
      - "The New Federal Court Rules and Their Relation to Current Practice in Missouri," 1938 (Box 19)
      - "The Principles Underlying the New Federal Rules of Civil Procedure" 1938 (Box 19)
      - "The Scope of Judicial Review," 1938 (Box 19)
      - "Discovery & Deposition, Pre-trial Practice & Summary Judgments," 1939 (Box 19)
      - "Discovery before Trial under the New Federal Rules," 1939 (Box 19)
      - "The Function of Pre-trial Procedure," 1939 (Box 19)
      - "Trends in Procedural Law," 1939 (Box 19)
    - 1940-1953
      - "Discovery before Trial," 1940 (Box 19)
      - "Improvement of Appellate Procedure," 1940 (Box 19)
      - "The Judicial Council as an Aid to the Administration of Justice," 1941 (Box 19)
      - "A Simplified System of Appellate Procedure," 1953 (Box 19)
      - "Cases and Materials on Code Pleading," 1953 (Box 19)
    - Undated
      - "Arguments, Decisions and Opinions on Appeal," undated (Box 19)
      - "The Ordinary Course of an Action at Law," undated (Box 19)